So how do I take things that I know I
should take seriously? How do I actually
take them seriously when it comes down
to it?
Which is when usually it's
not a big deal.
Well, you have to
start making an effort way before it
comes down to it.
So if you if you have reasons to take
something seriously, when you then need
to apply diligence
before as I said
those serious choices present themselves
and then start actually yeah reflecting
not forgetting and building up
determination that when those choices
present themselves, you don't choose
wrongly. But if if you just think that deciding
But if if you just think that deciding
to choose rightly
when the time is right and then not
doing anything in the meantime in terms
of
saying little knows to yourself saying
containing the mind
to the best of your abilities bit by
bit. If none of that's done, when the
time comes, the mind will choose what
the where the floodgates go basically
open and go. So there will be no no
means of saying no to that.
Determination will just be
any determination you made beforehand
will just be insignificant.
So you need to build it up
and work on it before that full on
pressure is felt
to go to a sensuality or ill will or bad
habits and so on.
And then how would you know if you're
being a bit too specific with
like you know obviously if you get way
too into kind of this one thing that I
think is unwholesome.
What do you mean? Can you be more
specific? >> [laughter]
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah. So say you say you're kind of
caught up with like oh this specific
activity is a problem
versus a more and you kind of make that
the focus.
You might be Well, if presumably you
mean to train in the precepts. So then
any activity that's that's pushing you
or bringing you closer
to breaking the precepts to compromising
the foundation of the training, well,
that's the activity that must be
restrained and abandoned.
If then you start picking on other
random activities for whatever,
you know.
You might not be very clear about it.
You just have a a need to say no to more
stuff. Then yeah, you could maybe
reflect on that and check cuz you might
not be necessary to say no to
everything. Like cuz they do you know
once they're saying no to the right
things, the momentum of that will want to make
the momentum of that will want to make
you start saying no to everything cuz
the more the better. That's how it
feels. The natural you know how the suitas
The natural you know how the suitas
describe like people first live
completely oblivious engaging with
sensuality left and right. Then they
kind of hear about it discern some value
of saying no to it, but now they want to
say no to everything.
Yeah, they'll stop eating. They'll stop
sleeping. They'll stop this. They'll
stop talking. They'll stop everything.
It's like when they becomes equally
ignorant. So so in order to to to reach well in
So so in order to to to reach well in
order to discern that balance, yeah,
first you have to say no to the obvious
core central cravings.
Then when the tendency to kind of turn
towards asceticism or or saying no to
even activities that are neutral,
when that comes up, well, you got to
recognize that and maybe say no to that
need. And that's how you stay in the in the
And that's how you stay in the in the
middle
between the two. But you can't
discern the middle of the bat. Like you
can't immediately start in a perfect
tune. You have to be like tightening
loosening tightening loosening until you
discern what's neither too tight nor too
loose. So trial and error is kind of inevitable
So trial and error is kind of inevitable
to to some extent. Obviously, the
clearer you are in terms of you know the
precepts, the purpose of the training,
the the the characteristics that need to
be discerned you know in phenomena as
the suitas talk about,
more accurate your trial and error will
be. But it's still going to be kind of you
But it's still going to be kind of you
know too tight too loose too tight too
loose until the the right tune is is
recognized and and played.
I'm wondering if the way that the suitas
when they talk about sensuality they
kind of divvy it up into you know like
speaking about it in terms of the five
senses and gives the impression that
it's always just like
focused on one. Like I really want to
taste this or I really want to see this.
But it seems like it's often a bit more
nuanced than that and that's
your reasons for engaging in sensuality
might be
almost
like something more more uh
inclusive. Let's say I'll give a
concrete example.
Some people say that they would have no
problem abstaining from sexuality
just on a physical basis,
but then it's actually the thought of
the implications about not having a
partner, not being loved, not having
kind of that reciprocal relationship.
That is the point where
they actually start to get
uncomfortable. The thought of just physically
The thought of just physically
abstaining doesn't present that.
And then that
that dimension of sexuality is not
um
it's not about like the coarse physical
sensations, but that doesn't mean it's not
but that doesn't mean it's not
sensual.
So well, that's the thing. It can it can
take myriad of forms depending on the
person. Yeah, even as the sutta says oh
man tastes vary. Like so somebody can be
into this into that. Somebody can prefer
this aspect or that aspect. The bottom
line is
if you find what your mind sensually
craves, you know for some people it would be
you know for some people it would be
very coarse or some people not so coarse
forms of it, but it's still going to be
the same root of the same craving same
type of craving.
So
if you start if if a person recognizes
that and then recognizes that kind of as
I said
mental dependence on those things like
oh you know I I've no problem giving
this up, but if I need to give that up,
that fills the mind with fear or you
know the as the sutta describe feels
like an abyss like a sudden precipice
like I can't do that. Then you realize
oh well that's that's where
where the work is.
So the mind has to get used to that and
see why. Because like
any attachment is a problem. Any
attachment is an obstruction.
Which means any aspect of sensuality
will be an obstruction.
Like oh it's not as coarse. That's fine.
But for you that is the current thing
that obstructs the mind from
development. I mean the suitas speak about it left
I mean the suitas speak about it left
and right constantly and even when the
you know you sometimes had people say
like oh well no this is just a minor
thing minor sensuality.
In that agama there was what Dhammadinna
brought out there was that monk that was
associating with the nuns enjoying their
company not doing anything not breaking
the rules you know technically.
And then the word got on to the Buddha
and then he said oh well that's not a
big deal. Like this doesn't need to be
confessed. It's not you know I'm not
engaging sexual not even having sexual
thoughts basically. It's more like just
company just friendship or whatever. And
the Buddha told him off. So you you got
to remember when did you hear me saying
that any aspect of sensuality is not an
obstacle? Where did I say that? Didn't I in so
Where did I say that? Didn't I in so
many occasions talk about sensuality and
giving similes of a burning bit uh the
bone the chopping block and and so on.
Because like you you can't compare with
others. Oh look this person's fine there
for like depends where your intention is
depending what state of your mind is.
So that's why
like some people would feel like oh it's
too much to give this up in regard to
the physical aspect. Some people
wouldn't have problem giving it up, but
they would have given they would have
problem giving up the mental aspects of
it. And then you realize well like you know
And then you realize well like you know
sure I can technically find a way around
this and say well look the precepts
doesn't say this.
But you know if I'm honest with myself
and see where my intention is rooted and
that it feels like an abyss cuz the
untrained mind doesn't want to go there.
Well, that is the Dhamma. That is the
training. Because
Because
when the Buddha told the Dhamma, there
were no rules for the first who knows
how many years literally. Monks didn't
have any rules.
Because everybody who understood the
intention of Dhamma understood what
intentions contradicted.
So the first rules were formed and
actually when they asked the Buddha to
form the rules preemptively, he said
that's impossible for the Tathagata to
to preemptively
address things that haven't occurred or
happened. The Dhamma is the guide in and of itself
The Dhamma is the guide in and of itself
for those who see it.
You know exactly what what's obstructing
it and you exactly what isn't
obstructing. So
So
then the rules were formed later on when
basically the whole kind of the direct
contact and recognition of the
principles of the Dhamma would be coming
obscured through
sheer kind of loss of quality of people
admitted and so on. It's inevitable.
So in this case it's the same. Like you
could say well look
friendship or relationship it's not
against the precept. Keep the precepts.
We both keep the precepts. We're both
celebrate and or
to the best of our ability and so on.
It's like okay, but if you're the one
who wants to practice for like
liberation from suffering.
By the way if if that person is not
interested in that, then none of this
applies. >> [clears throat]
>> [clears throat]
>> As goes without saying.
>> [laughter]
>> But if a person is interested, then it
doesn't really matter if there is a
specified rule against it or not. What
matters is is this coming out of
attachment to craving? I mean the answer
is evident and obvious anybody honest
enough to admit it.
So so that's that's what becomes like
the criteria. It's like, "Well, it's not
a problem,
but it is problem for me
because for whatever reason, and I don't
need to psychologize to find out why my
mind really wants this and fears giving
it up.
It's enough that I see that it is so.
And which means, okay, so now we have to
train you in in contemplating losing
those things, giving those things up
until you calm down. And then you might
realize, "Oh yeah, I never really wanted
it that much. I never really cared about
it that much." But it wasn't about you.
It was about training that animal that
for whatever reason wants this, doesn't
want that.
Um and then uh you know, it's not going
to be pleasant working through that.
But it's it's the only way cuz pretty
much like your attachments tell you
where the direction of the practice is.
So, whether there is a rule or whether
there is an instruction, whether some
teacher told you about it or not, again,
if you understood the principle of
training correctly,
principle of taming, you don't need any
more instruction.
And that's exactly what the Buddha said
to some monks and nuns.
Uh it says, "Whatever
whatever leads to uh lust,
away from non-lust, that's not the
Dhamma. Whatever leads away from lust, that's
Whatever leads away from lust, that's
the Dhamma. Whatever leads towards
hatred, delusion, whatever leads away
from it, and so on."
And laid out is like I don't know, a
dozen or so standards which anybody at
any point in any culture, in any future
can use to discern what's in line with
the Dhamma and what isn't in line with
the Dhamma.
And that removes all the loopholes, all
the technicalities, all the things that
were not stated in the suttas. This is
all gone.
Cuz the principle is stated and it's
all-inclusive. Like how the Buddha gave the simile like
Like how the Buddha gave the simile like
an elephant footprint includes all the
other smaller footprints in itself.
And that's the point cuz sooner or later
person will come. Everybody will come at
at that kind of
like a crossroad in a way. It's like,
"Oh yeah, you know, I'm keeping the
precepts, but there are certain things that are
but there are certain things that are
not against the precepts, but I do
repeatedly see, recognize, and and um
see, recognize, and and um
discern that the mind for whatever
reason really depends on this, really
wants it, really protects it. It's
really attached to it, basically.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh but because it's not against the
precepts, it's not against the training,
I won't deal with it. I'll deal with
these other secondary things. It's like
you'll only go so far with that type of
attitude. You have to recognize it. Like
you're not going to you're not going to
fix the attachments overnight.
It's not going to be enough to just uh
say no to this and never again.
Yeah, you can try,
but the point is No, no, no. I need to
like
train the mind
away from these things.
I can't just say no and and and dismiss
everything and make these
blind the tongue and determinations and
just stick through it, power through.
It's like, "No, no. The mind for
whatever reason
like the example you gave, values,
wants, needs relationships.
So, I recognize that as an objective
phenomenon, as a fact.
Um I can't just I mean, I can say no,
but again, the animal will still want
it. No, I need to contemplate
No, I need to contemplate
and make, as I said, the diligent effort
to first not blindly pursuing the
relationships and then contemplating the danger, the
and then contemplating the danger, the
weight,
the burden,
the implications of it repeatedly until
the mind's like,
"Oh yeah, you're right." And then it
will forget it. It will forget next day.
And then I have to do it again and
again. And that's how you train the mind
away. That's like again, the suttas
describe that of
just in broad terms as the suttas are
very broad. It's like bringing up
certain perceptions
of impermanence, of loss, of decay, of
so
that pretty much again, as I said,
encompass anything you might be attached
to or interested in. Undermines it.
So, you're not just bringing up a
perception of impermanency in a
theoretical abstract manner, ah anicca
or
but you're finding what the mind depends
on and then you are undermining it
by a gradual controlled perception of
impermanence of those things while the
mind wants them.
So that the mind stops wanting them.
And so that you can actually so that
both of you, you and your mind can
experience unshakable peace.